mivu.org 2018-08-20

# Privacy Policy - Michigan Virtual

BY ACCESSING ANY OF OUR WEBSITES, YOU AGREE TO THE TERMS OF THIS PRIVACY STATEMENT AND TERMS OF SERVICE. OUR PRIVACY POLICY AND TERMS OF SERVICE MAY CHANGE ACCORDING TO THE TERMS DESCRIBED BELOW AND ALL CHANGES ARE EFFECTIVE IMMEDIATELY. PLEASE READ THE ENTIRE STATEMENT BEFORE USING THIS WEBSITE OR PROVIDING ANY INFORMATION THROUGH ANY OF THE SITES LISTED BELOW.

This page describes the ways in which _Michigan Virtual™_ , a Michigan nonprofit corporation, and all of its divisions (collectively referred to here as “ _Michigan Virtual_ ,” “we,” “us” or “our”) handle information it obtains about individuals through the websites it operates, including:

michiganvirtual.org (and all sub-domains of michiganvirtual.org)  
mivu.org (and all sub-domains of mivu.org)  
mivhs.org  
mvlri.org  
micourses.org

We provide a variety of information, features, and functions (the “Services”) through these websites.

This page does not necessarily reflect the ways in which we collect and use information by means other than these websites. If you have questions about the ways in which we collect information by other means, please contact us using the contact information in this statement. The practices relating to persons with separate agreements with _Michigan Virtual_ or its affiliates are separately covered in those agreements.

### Information Michigan Virtual collects

The information we collect will depend on what you do when visiting our sites. EXCEPT AS STATED IN THIS STATEMENT, WE WILL NOT COLLECT PERSONALLY IDENTIFIABLE INFORMATION ABOUT YOU WHEN YOU VISIT OUR SITES UNLESS YOU CHOOSE TO PROVIDE SUCH INFORMATION TO US. You are free to visit our sites without providing personally identifiable information. However, if you would like to access our Services, in some cases you must first register or create an account or learning profile with _Michigan Virtual_. When you register or create an account or learning profile, we will request certain personal information. Requests can include but are not limited to your name, address, city, state, zip code, county, email address, age, home or other contact information, school contact information, gender, and parent/guardian contact information. In some cases, the sponsoring party funding your participation in the course (a “Sponsoring Party”) may provide this or other information about you to us. We may use this information to create an account or learning profile and issue you an access ID and password. If you are paying with a credit card, we also will collect your credit card number (employing industry standard security and encryption technologies), billing information and email address to process your payment.

Personal information better enables us to provide you with content relevant to your interests and provides us with aggregate demographic data that _Michigan Virtual_ uses to improve the services offered to users. Users may change their personal information at any time by using the provided interface once they are logged in and as often as necessary. If users are unable to log in and change their information themselves, they will be able to send an email to [customercare@michiganvirtual.org](mailto:customercare@michiganvirtual.org) or contact us at the telephone number or address below for assistance.

In addition to registration, _Michigan Virtual_ may, from time to time, request personal information for purposes such as the provision of customer service, billing, network management, customer surveys, newsletter subscriptions, offers of related services, and other exchanges of information. Users may opt out of receiving future promotional mailings at any time. Please see below for User Options – Opt Out.

_Michigan Virtual_ gathers information about all users collectively, such as what areas users visit most frequently and what services users’ access most often. _Michigan Virtual_ automatically logs IP addresses, session sources, and other data which tracks users’ access to our sites. We analyze these logs for sales and marketing purposes as well as system performance monitoring. These logs are analyzed for the overall, aggregate trends they reveal about our customers, not for the behaviors of individual users.

### Privacy of children

The _Michigan Virtual_ policy is to limit the collection of personal information from children in substantial agreement with the Children’s Online Privacy and Protection Act (COPPA). Children ages 12 and under will not knowingly be allowed to register with _Michigan Virtual_ or create an account without their parent’s permission. Before children ages 12 and under may participate in any Services requiring registration (e.g., creating or enrolling in a course, chat rooms, message boards or other forums), the child’s school must first obtain the parent’s permission and that permission may allow us to collect and maintain the child’s information. If at any time after a parent gives permission, the parent desires to review the child’s personal information, request that it be deleted, or refuse to allow any further collection of the child’s information, the parent may contact the school’s representative for _Michigan Virtual_  with such a request. If you have additional questions regarding your child’s use of his or her account, you may contact the school’s representative or _Michigan Virtual_. Please see below for our contact information.

_Michigan Virtual_ abides by COPPA and the regulations under it. You can obtain more information about COPPA from the [Federal Trade Commission](https://www.ftc.gov/tips-advice/business-center/guidance/complying-coppa-frequently-asked-questions).

### What does Michigan Virtual do with the information it collects?

The User ID you select during registration must be used to log in and participate in a Service or course. Once you log into our Blackboard site, you may be identified to the instructor and other students in that course by your full name in areas such as discussion forums, email lists, web conferences, and other places where participant names appear. Please remember that any information that is disclosed in these areas becomes available to the instructor and other students in that course. Blackboard has a user accessible directory feature. Anyone with a Blackboard account can choose to share their Blackboard profile information in this directory. You can turn on or off this feature once logged into Blackboard. You should exercise caution when deciding to disclose your personal information.

_Michigan Virtual_ hosts, or provides links to, chat rooms, forums and message boards. Our online instructors, instructor services, and student services staff monitor and respond to user email sent to them and monitor and participate with users in threaded discussions and other online forums. _Michigan Virtual_ may monitor or edit the contents of a user’s email or threaded discussions or other online forums as required for normal maintenance of any of our websites or in the good-faith belief that such action is necessary to:

  1. Comply with the law or comply with legal process served on _Michigan Virtual_ _._
  2. Protect and defend the rights or property of _Michigan Virtual_ _._
  3. Act to protect the personal safety of our guests or the public.

If you are a _Michigan Virtual_  student, your grades in _Michigan Virtual_ courses will be reported to your mentor and your school and/or sponsoring institution. Except as described further in this statement, the personal information you supply to _Michigan Virtual_ will not be given, sold, rented, loaned, or otherwise disclosed to any third parties outside of _Michigan Virtual_ , except when we have your permission or under special circumstances, such as when we believe in good faith that disclosure is reasonably necessary to:

  1. Comply with the legal process.
  2. Enforce the Terms of Use.
  3. Respond to claims that any content on our sites violates the rights of third parties.
  4. Protect the rights, property, or personal safety of _Michigan Virtual_ , its users or the public.

_Michigan Virtual_ may use aggregated personal information to determine the demographics of our users and to distribute statistics and general marketplace information about _Michigan Virtual_. We will use commercially reasonable efforts to ensure that these demographics do not identify any specific user.

In accordance with Michigan’s State School Aid Act, _Michigan Virtual_ offers student courses as part of its effort to serve as a statewide laboratory and quality model of instruction for implementing virtual learning solutions. As such, it is possible that research will be conducted on a course in which students are enrolled or on students’ online experience. Non-personally identifiable data will be shared with researchers for these purposes. If for any reason a student does not want to participate in research activities or does not want his or her data to be used for research purposes, please send an email at any time to customercare@michiganvirtual.org. In that email, please include the student’s first and last name, the email address the student uses when signing into the Student Learning Portal, as well as a sentence indicating that the student does not want to participate in research activities. Please use “Research” in the subject line of the email. A student’s participation in research is voluntary and there is no penalty if a student does not want to participate.

_Michigan Virtual_ will abide by the student privacy guidelines set forth by the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA). The following persons have access to student records:

  * _Michigan Virtual_ Board of Directors members.
  * President and CEO, the _Michigan Virtual_ administrative team and professional staff of _Michigan Virtual_.
  * Appropriate administrative support staff members and other professionals who have a legitimate educational or legal interest in student records as designated by the President and CEO.

Certain non-personal information regarding users is recorded by the standard operation of the Internet servers hosting our sites. This information may be used to provide visitors to our sites with an enhanced, online experience. _Michigan Virtual_ may disclose aggregated user statistics, in order to describe the service to prospective partners, advertisers, and other third parties and for other lawful purposes.

### Cookies

A cookie is a small data file that certain websites write to your computer when you visit them. A cookie file can contain information such as a user ID that the site uses to track the pages you’ve visited. A cookie can’t read data from your hard disk or generally read cookie files created by other sites. _Michigan Virtual_ uses cookies to track information about visitors to our sites, such as the pages they visit and product information they view. We may do this through the use of cookies, flash cookies or pixel tags. The information we collect helps us better manage the sites, provides ease of use of the sites for the user, and provides more effective marketing to the user.

Our Blackboard course management system uses cookies as a unique user and session identifier. These cookies are not “persistent,” which is to say that they are not permanently stored on the user’s computer. The Blackboard cookie is destroyed when the browser session is closed.

Most or all browsers permit you to disable or reject cookies. You can do this by setting the preferences in the browser. Use the “help” feature of your browser to obtain more information about cookies. Visitors to our websites always have the option of disabling cookies via their browser preferences, but some of the Services will not work if you have cookies disabled.

### JavaScript and Web browser support

_Michigan Virtual_ websites are designed to provide you with the information and services you expect: web pages that are accessible, easy-to-use, error-free and provide appropriate security. To achieve this goal, we’ve developed our site in accordance with widely accepted web standards.

If our pages do not function correctly or appear broken, you may have JavaScript turned off, or you may be using a web browser that is not compatible with the security or development standards of this site. Most _Michigan Virtual_ websites and web applications use JavaScript and require that you allow JavaScript in your web browser in order for them to function correctly.

### Log files

We or our hosting provider may collect traffic information from visitors for statistical analysis and site improvement. When you access a site, we or our hosting provider may collect information about your visit in a log file on a server. Log file information may include, but is not limited to, internet protocol (IP) addresses, browser type, internet service provider (ISP), referring/exit pages, platform type, date/time stamp, and the number of clicks. We or our hosting providers use this information to analyze trends, administer the site, track users’ movements in the aggregate, and gather demographic information for aggregate use. IP addresses and other log file information are not linked to personally identifiable information. We do not try to track users or to identify users individually, but we or our hosting providers do review this information to understand overall trends and to determine what kinds of content are popular and useful to users.

### Outsourcing providers

We may use outside shipping or other outsourcing providers to process and ship orders or perform other functions. We require that these outsourcing providers not retain, share, store or use personally identifiable information for any secondary purposes, except for backup and recovery operations. Although we use good faith efforts to ensure compliance by its outsourcing providers, we cannot, and will not, be responsible to users for misuse of personally identifiable information by such outsourcing providers.

### Specific services

We may have agreements with other parties to provide specific services. When you use such services, we may share personally identifiable information with such parties. In such cases, we will use good faith efforts to restrict the information provided to that which is necessary for the provision of such services.

### Supplementation of information

We sometimes supplement the information we receive from you with other information we receive from third-party sources, such as credit card issuers or clearinghouses.

### User options – opt out

A user may opt to cease receiving future promotional mailings by sending an email to [unsubscribe@michiganvirtual.org](mailto:unsubscribe@michiganvirtual.org) and including his or her full name, User ID (if applicable), email address and the name of the mailing he or she no longer wishes to receive in the subject or message area. A user may also contact us at the telephone number or address below. _Michigan Virtual_ reserves the right to send all users non-promotional email related to business practices and systems operations, such as outage notifications and security warnings, even if the user has opted out of promotional mailings.

Visiting any of our websites and providing personal information sufficient to be able to email information to you will be sufficient to create an existing business relationship with you for purposes of complying with the CAN-SPAM Act of 2003 regarding unsolicited commercial email.

### Response times

We will use commercially reasonable efforts to make timely changes you may request regarding your personal information. Many such changes are accomplished using batch processing (i.e., collecting a number of similar change requests and making all such changes at once), so the changes may not be immediately effective. If you require an immediate change to your personally identifiable information and are unable to make such a change using the available site resources, please contact us using the information below.

### Links to other websites

You should be aware that when you are on our sites, you could be directed or provided with links to other sites that are beyond our control and have no affiliation or business relationship with _Michigan Virtual_. _Michigan Virtual_ is not responsible for the content or information collection practices of these non- _Michigan Virtual_ operated websites. Please note that these non- _Michigan Virtual_ operated websites’ privacy policies may substantially differ from this statement. We encourage you to review and understand the privacy practices of any website before providing to them any personal information.

### Access to your information

_Michigan Virtual_ offers users the ability to change the information collected during registration or profile creation. Users may change their personal information at any time by using the provided browser interface, once they are logged in and as often as necessary. Remember that you may have to log into multiple _Michigan Virtual_ hosted sites to correct or change your personal information depending on the different Services you have chosen to access. If a user is unable to log in and change his or her information him or herself, he or she should send an email to [customercare@michiganvirtual.org](mailto:customercare@michiganvirtual.org) for assistance or contact us using the address or telephone number below.

### Security

Our websites use security measures that we believe are reasonably designed to protect against the loss, misuse and alteration of the information under our control. Personal information is stored in a restricted access, secure database and only _Michigan Virtual_ staff or other authorized personnel supporting your enrollment or Services are authorized to have access to that database. _Michigan Virtual_ employs security measures and industry-standard encryption for all online purchases. All users are strongly advised to use Web browsers with 128-bit or better encryption features.

_Michigan Virtual_ has placed all of its web and application servers inside of locked cages or rooms within commercial data centers. We deploy firewalls, intrusion detection and other unpublished security measures to control access to personal data stored within our enterprise. If you have any concerns regarding the security of any _Michigan Virtual_ system, please send an email to [customercare@michiganvirtual.org](mailto:customercare@michiganvirtual.org), and we will reply to you within two business days.

### European Union data protection

If you reside in or are a citizen of a member state of the European Union, by registering or creating an account to use the Services, you expressly agree that the personal information you provide may be transferred and stored in countries outside the EU, including the United States. If you do not agree to this statement, please do not use any of our sites or services for which registration or account creation is required.

### Michigan Virtual Privacy Policy statement changes

If _Michigan Virtual_ changes this privacy statement, we will post those changes on this website and the revised privacy statement will be effective immediately upon posting. By using any of our websites or services, you agree to this change mechanism. If you do not agree to this change mechanism, please do not use our sites or services. Your continued use of our sites or services following the posting of changes to these terms will mean you accept those changes.

### Service limitations

You are not permitted to associate any _Michigan Virtual_ -provided account, service or course with any adult material of any sort. This includes, but is not limited to, such things as nudity, any site, page, image or service, and any text, image or likeness suggesting sexual and or illegal acts of any sort. We do not permit any _Michigan Virtual_ user account to store, use, contain, promote or display pornography, adult novelties, adult toys, XXX material, Gorean, bondage, BDSM, anything illegal, bigotry, racism, hatred, profanity or any material that may be insulting to another person(s) or company, or depicts the exploitation of minors (children under 18 years of age). No spamming is allowed, no harassing, threatening or illegal activities are tolerated. Any user accounts found to be violating these service limitations will be terminated without warning or recourse at the sole discretion of _Michigan Virtual_.

### In addition, we do not allow:

  * File Storage — Any User Account found to be storing files for use on other websites will be terminated without notice or recourse, at the sole discretion of _Michigan Virtual_. User Accounts found to be storing files renamed, or modified in any way, to bypass _Michigan Virtual_ file restrictions will be terminated without notice or recourse, at the sole discretion of _Michigan Virtual_. The only files that may be stored or uploaded to a _Michigan Virtual_ server are those that directly pertain to the teaching, learning, or class activity for which the User Account has been granted access to a _Michigan Virtual_ server or application.
  * Copyrighted or Trademarked materials — NO copyrighted or trademarked materials may be stored on _Michigan Virtual_ servers, unless the account owner is the sole legal owner of the Copyright or Trademark and can reasonably demonstrate Ownership or legal permission for use, on demand.

Material linked to User Accounts must be appropriate and be able to be legally viewed and used by all ages. User Accounts found to be in violation of any portion of this section can and will be terminated without notice or recourse at the sole discretion of _Michigan Virtual_. In such cases, where an account is terminated for service violations as detailed in this or the following two sections; no refunds or credit will be offered, and the User acknowledges that their account termination may result in course failure as well as other disciplinary action.

### Use of Michigan Virtual servers

_Michigan Virtual_ servers may be used for lawful purposes only. Transmission, storage or distribution of any information, data, or material in violation of any applicable law or regulation is prohibited. This includes, but is not limited to Copyrighted material, trademarks, trade secrets or other intellectual property rights used without proper authorization; material that is obscene, defamatory, constitutes an illegal threat or violates export control laws.

### Michigan Virtual network security

Violations of system or network security are prohibited and may result in criminal and civil liability. Examples include but are not limited to the following: unauthorized access, use, probing, or scanning of systems security or authentication measures, data, or traffic; interference with service to any user, host, or network including, without limitation, mail bombing, flooding, deliberate attempts to overload a system, broadcast attacks; forging of any TCP-IP packet header or any part of the header information in an email or a newsgroup posting.

### Contact Michigan Virtual

If you have any questions about this privacy statement or the privacy practices of this website, please contact us electronically at [customercare@michiganvirtual.org](mailto:customercare@michiganvirtual.org) or write to us or call us.

Michigan Virtual  
3101 Technology Blvd., Suite G  
Lansing, MI 48910  
888.889.2840

In the event that you are concerned about how data you have provided to _Michigan Virtual_ or one of its divisions through our sites and services have been used, please contact us electronically at [customercare@michiganvirtual.org](mailto:customercare@michiganvirtual.org) or write to the postal address listed above.

[Last Updated on 03/13/2017]
